Hello everyone and
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco. My name
is Catherine and today we're
talking about helping
other people. That's right,
we are going to
volunteer and to help other
people that maybe don't
have as much as we do and
so this is a way to give
back to the community.
That's right, so this is
an intermediate level
lesson and before we get
going, we have a phrase to
preview and today
is vocabulary preview.
Very vocabulary preview. All
right, so on vocabulary preview
today we have this
phrase a soup kitchen or
it's a noun soup kitchen.
That's right, a soup
kitchen is a place.
Basically it is a place where
volunteers can help cook
and serve people who
don't have enough
money to feed themselves.
Okay, so that's a soup
kitchen. It's basically a place
where people can get
free food. That's right.
Okay, so this is where
we're going to be today.
We are at a soup kitchen
and we're going to hear a
couple of people talking about
helping out at a soup kitchen.
Let's listen.
Thanks a lot for pitching
in once again Judy.
We really appreciate
your help. It seems that at
this time of year there
are more and more people
who are struggling
to make ends meet.
There aren't many professional
chefs like you who are so generous
with their time.
Don't be silly Mark.
I'm more than happy to
debate my time to a good cause.
Volunteering at the soup kitchen
has been really rewarding for me.
You know it's satisfying to provide good
meals for those who are less fortunate.
I feel like I'm really making a
difference in some small way.
Well, your skills are
definitely appreciated here.
The people who come
here have fallen on
hard times and a
delicious hot meal can really
bolster their spirits.
Wow, that smells great.
The needy are sure
lucky to have you.
Thanks, Mark.
Here you go. Enjoy your meal.
Thank you, my dear.
Oh, this looks lovely. You're welcome.
Hello, sir. Today we have George.
What are you doing here?
Hey, Judy. I'll have a
little of everything. Thanks.
Smells great. George, seriously.
What are you doing here? I haven't
seen you since our divorce was finalized.
You've got no right to be here.
You're hardly homeless. Don't be like that,
Judy. I really miss your home cooking.
All right, we're back. So obviously this
person was in George. He didn't really need
the food, but apparently
I think he's divorced from
his wife and he was like,
"Oh, I need your food.
" But other people that
were there were very much
in need of this food. So
why don't we take a look
at some of the words and
phrases on language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
Well, we've got a
couple of interesting
words here at the beginning
that have to do with volunteering
or helping other people.
The first phrase we
have actually is to pitch in.
That's right. To pitch in.
So when you pitch in, that's
a way of saying helping, right?
That's right. To help. So
I could ask you for your
help with something. I
could say, "Hey, Marco,
can you pitch in a little of your
time with this project I have?
" Okay. So dedicate
or to help to pitch in.
So when you pitch
in, you are helping.
This is a really common phrase,
very colloquial though, right?
To pitch in, that's right. Okay.
And then moving on another
adjective when a person likes
to help or gives money to the
poor, that person is generous.
That's right. So
generous is an adjective.
That means a person can
be generous or an effort
can be generous. For
example, a very famous
generous person is
Mother Teresa of Calcutta.
Well, I'll say you weren't
Buffett, but both of
them are very generous.
Mother Teresa for giving
back to the poor and
weren't Buffett for donating
most of his money.
Okay, very good.
So that is a sign of a
person that is generous.
So usually generous people like
Warren Buffet, you say he gave
away his fortune to people
that didn't have money.
We call these people
the less fortunate.
That's right. So as you
said, we've got three
words here that mean
poor people basically.
And we don't like to say poor people
in English because it's not very nice.
You know, people can't control
their situation in many cases.
And it's more of a
situation of not having
what others have. And so one
way to say this is less fortunate.
Okay. So a person that's less fortunate
is a person that's poor. That's right.
So I could say, for
example, we often try to help
the less fortunate by
volunteering our time. Okay.
So fortunate is a way
of saying that you have
fortune or you have
luck. So if you say you are
very fortunate, that means
that you are very lucky.
That's right. Okay. So
less fortunate means poor.
And another way of saying
that somebody is poor,
you say that person
is needy. Needy.
So this probably makes
you think of the word need,
to need, and you're right.
This comes from need.
So someone who is needy
needs things, needs money,
needs help, needs food.
Okay. Even attention, right?
Somebody that's needy might need a lot
of attention all the time. That's right.
So this could actually be a
bad thing. Someone who's
needy says, look at me.
Look at me. Look at me.
Oh my gosh. Look at me. Listen to
me. And that can be very annoying.
Okay. So the needy and now finally a
very common word to say that somebody at
very poor doesn't have a place
to live, doesn't have a home.
You say that person is homeless.
Homeless literally
means without a home.
And so we often talk about the
homeless as being a group of people.
We want to help in
society because the
homeless live on the
streets, they live in public.
And in the winter and
times when it's really,
really cold, it's very
dangerous for them.
So the homeless are
a group that people try
to help with these soup
kitchens and shelters.
Okay. Very good. So a lot of interesting
words come in phrases. They're very useful.
So why don't we go
back, listen to this dialogue
again and we'll be
back in a little bit with
fluency builder. Thanks
a lot for pitching in
once again, Judy. We
really appreciate your help.
It seems that at this time
of year, there are more
and more people who are
struggling to make ends meet.
There aren't many professional chefs like
you who are so generous with their time.
Don't be silly, Mark. I'm more than
happy to debate my time to a good cause.
Volunteering at the soup
kitchen has been really
rewarding for me. You
know, it's satisfying to
provide good meals for
those who are less fortunate.
I feel like I'm really making a
difference in some small way.
Well, your skills are definitely appreciated
here. The people who come here have
fallen on hard times and
a delicious hot meal can
really bolster their spirits.
Wow, that smells great.
The needy are sure
lucky to have you.
Thanks, Mark. Here
you go. Enjoy your meal.
Thank you, my dear. Oh, this looks lovely.
You're welcome. Hello, sir. Today we have
George. What are you doing here? Hey, Judy.
I'll have a little of everything. Thanks.
Smells great. George, seriously.
What are you doing here?
I haven't seen you since
our divorce was finalized.
You've got no right to be here.
You're hardly homeless.
Don't be like that, Judy.
I really miss your home cooking.
All right, we're back. So on
Fluency Builder, today we have
three key phrases. So we're
going to take a look at those now.
Fluency Builder. Okay.
So what is our first phrase?
Our first phrase comes from
the beginning of the
dialogue with Mark who says,
you know, there are some
people who are struggling
to make ends meet.
So the phrase here is to
make ends meet. Okay.
To make ends meet.
So I have, so if you take a
look at this phrase, it's very
hard to determine
what that actually means.
What does it mean?
Well, think about a string.
If you want to make a
circle out of that string, you
have to connect the
ends, right? And I think of
that as being about your income
and the money that you spend.
I cannot make ends meet.
If I earn $10 every week, but I
spend 15 on my house and my food.
Right. Okay. So not being able to make ends
meet means you spend more than you earn.
And that's not about
cars and fancy TVs.
That's about your house,
your heat, your bills, your food.
But I say, I've been able to
make ends meet for a while
now because I have a
pretty good job. Okay.
So to make ends meet is to be
able to pay for your necessities.
Okay. But he can't make ends meet means
he can't support himself financially. Okay.
Very good. So to make
ends meet is pretty much
to satisfy your basic
necessities financially, financially.
Okay. Very good. And moving on when
we were talking about generosity and people
helping out, you know,
if you help people that
are less fortunate, you are
making a difference in a small way.
Okay. So this is a phrase that we hear
all the time in the states. I'm not sure if
it's the same in other
English speaking countries,
but it's a very popular
phrase. We talk about
making a difference or
trying to make a difference.
And it's not very
clear what a difference
really is, but generally
this means doing good
things for other people.
Okay. Okay. So celebrities
try to make a difference with
their money and their fame.
Some people try
to make a difference
by working at homeless
shelters or at soup kitchens.
And so there are many
different ways to make
a difference, but it's
basically the idea that you
volunteer or you give
money to help other people.
Okay. Very good. So
even if, for example, you
recycle, you can say
you're making a difference
in the environment. That's
right. You're making a difference.
Usually a difference
is a positive thing.
So keep that in mind. Very good.
And for the last phrase
on fluency builder today,
we say that people who come
here have fallen on hard times.
So people that have
fallen on hard times.
What does it mean if
you fall on hard times?
Well, basically, hard times are difficulties,
right? So not being able to make
ends meet, not being able to
pay for your food and your housing.
And so we have the verb to fall.
You've fallen on hard
times because you've gone
from a place where
you're comfortable to a
lower place, a place
where life is really hard.
Right. And so think of
this as a fixed phrase.
He fell on hard times
or they fell on hard times.
This means they don't
have much money or they
can't support themselves or
they went bankrupt, for example.
So somebody that loses their job may
have fallen on hard times. That's right.
Okay. And there's one
more phrase here that
deserves a little attention.
We heard this word to bolster.
To bolster is a verb
that means to improve.
So a hot meal can
really bolster their spirits.
It means it can make
them feel better.
So to bolster their spirits
means to make them
feel happier, to lift
their spirits. That's right.
Exactly what you said to
make them feel happier.
Okay. Awesome. So a
lot of interesting phrases
there, ways that you
can talk in English about
making a difference,
about volunteering, very
interesting stuff, very good
for conversations between
friends and family. So
why don't we go back,
listen to the dialogue again and
we'll be back to talk a little bit more.
Thanks a lot for pitching in once again
Judy. We really appreciate your help.
It seems that at this time
of year there are more
and more people who are
struggling to make ends meet.
There aren't many professional chefs like
you who are so generous with their time.
Don't be silly Mark. I'm more than
happy to debate my time to a good cause.
Volunteering at the soup
kitchen has been really
rewarding for me. You
know it's satisfying to
provide good meals for
those who are less fortunate.
I feel like I'm really
making a difference
in some small way. Well
your skills are definitely
appreciated here. The
people who come here have
fallen on hard times and
a delicious hot meal can
really bolster their spirits.
Wow that smells great.
The needy are sure lucky to have you.
Thanks Mark. Here you go enjoy your meal.
Thank you my dear.
Oh this looks lovely. You're welcome.
Hello sir. Today we have George.
What are you doing here?
Hey Judy.
I'll have a little of everything. Thanks.
Smells great. George seriously.
What are you doing here?
I haven't seen you since
our divorce was finalized.
You've got no right to be here.
You're hardly homeless.
Don't be like that Judy.
I really miss your home cooking.
All right we're back so
talking about volunteering.
Have you ever done
any volunteer work?
I have. I've done quite a bit actually.
Yeah we're what what have you done?
Back when I was living
in the United States in
Chicago I used to cook
for a homeless shelter every
week so I would bring
food every Thursday.
So you cook at home and you
bring the food over to the shelter.
That's right so the
shelter had a kitchen
but they used donations
from people because
there are so many people
who came there for food
and once a month I would
volunteer to also serve the food.
Okay. So I would
bring lasagna or pasta
things that most people
like and then once a month
I would sit down
with people and talk.
A lot of people are lonely
when they're in homeless shelters
because they come alone
or maybe as a mother
and her child and it's
nice to also come and sit
and talk to them. No
it's very interesting and I
think volunteering is a
much better solution than for
example just giving up
money to poor people or
something like that. I don't
think that's really the solution.
I think you should
dedicate your time
and your energy to making a
difference like in the dialogue.
Well and I think
that the other benefit
is for you the volunteer
because it changes your
perspective on poverty
and on humanity and you
think about well you
know I could be this person.
He was a banker two years
ago and now he doesn't
have a house and so
I think it has a positive
effect on everybody
involved. Yeah for sure no
I think it's a very
rewarding experience and
I think English pod
definitely supports that you
should volunteer you
should make a difference
and I think we can all
help each other right.
That's right and let us know
have you ever volunteered
what kind of volunteer
work have you done?
Has it been environmental
or social? Let us know in our
website EnglishPod.com we hope to
see you there. All right bye everyone. Bye.